<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proclamacion diuised by the kynges highnes with thaduise of his most honourable counsaile, for the restraynte of shootyng in handgunnes</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1546</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1509-1547 : Henry VIII)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1546</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 3 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69310</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7808</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109274</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844924</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844924</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9782</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69310)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9782)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 10:21, 152:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proclamacion diuised by the kynges highnes with thaduise of his most honourable counsaile, for the restraynte of shootyng in handgunnes</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1546</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1509-1547 : Henry VIII)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Tho. Berthelet regius impressor excudebat. Cum priuilegio ad imprimendu[m] solum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1546]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Society of Antiquaries.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reels 10 and 152 (Society of Antiquaries copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Pistol shooting --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="royal_proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:9782:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->
            <head>A proclamacion diuiſed by the kynges highnes, with thaduiſe of his moſt honourable counſaile, for the reſtraynte of ſhootyng in handegunnes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here the kyng our moſte drad ſoueraigne lorde, conſiderying how expedient it was to haue his louyng ſubiectes practiſed and exerciſed in the feate of ſhootyng of hande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunnes and hagbuſſhes, as well for the defence of this his highnes realme and other his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>almes and dominions, as for the annoyaunce of his maieſtees ennemies in time of warre and hoſtilitee, dyd by his highneſſe proclamacion ſet foorth, by the aduiſe of his maieſtees counſell, accordyng to the act and ſtatute made at Weſtminſter the .xxviii. daie of April, in the .xxxi. yere of his moſt gracious reigne, gyue lycence and libertee to all his maieſtees ſubiectes, borne within his graces dominions, being of the age of .xvi. yeres, and vpwardes, That they and euery of them, from and after the ſaied proclamation made, might laufully ſhoote in handgunnes and hagbuſhes, without incurryng any forfaiture loſſe or daunger for the ſame: any ſtatute therof made before to the contrary not withſtandyng, as by the ſame proclamation more at large dooth and maie appeere. For as much as it hath pleaſed god to remoue from vs the plage of warre, and to ſende vnto vs a ryght honourable and profitable peace, whiche (by goddes grace) ſhall continue to his glory, and to the honour and ſuretee of his maieſtee and his ſucceſſion, and to the quiete and benefyte of this realme: His moſte royall maieſtee therefore by this his highneſſe preſent proclamation, ſette foorth by the aduiſe of his maieſtees counſaile, accordyng to the act aboue mencioned, dooeth not only make voyde the ſayed former proclamacion, but alſo ſtraightly chargeth and commaundeth all and ſyngular his maieſtees ſubiectes, that they or any of them, from the laſte daie of Auguſt next commyng, ſhall not ſhoote in any hand gounnes, hagbuſſhes, or other gunnes, nor vſe or haue the ſame contrarye to the tenour fourme and effecte of his graciouſe lawe and ſtatute made in the parlyament begunne at Weſtmynſter the .xvi. daie of Ianu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie, and contynued vntill the fyrſt daie of Aprill, in the .xxxiii. yere of his moſte gracious reigne: Excepte any of his ſaied louyng ſubiectes haue his graces lycence vnder his great Seale for the ſame, or otherwyſe lycenced or auctoryſed by the ſame ſtatute made the fyrſt daie of Aprill, in the ſaied .xxxiii. yere of his ſaied mooſte gracious reygne, vppon the peyne of the forfayture mencioned in the ſame Statute. Wyllyng and commaundynge all and ſyngular Iuſtices of the peace, Mayres, Shyreffes, Bayllyffes, Conſtables, and all other his maieſtees officers, myniſters, and ſubiectes, to haue ſpeciall regarde to the dewe exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cucion of this proclamation, as they tender his maieſtees pleaſure, and wolle aunſwere for the contrarye al theyr perilles.</p>
            <closer>God ſaue the kynge.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="license">
            <p>Tho. Berthelet regius impreſſor excudebat.</p>
            <p>Cum priuilegio ad imprimendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſolum.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
